Guide to the Zygmunt Haupt Papers
Department of Special Collections
Zygmunt Haupt papers
1949-1976
M0356
Haupt, Zygmunt, 1907-1975
9.25 linear feet
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Correspondence, literary manuscripts, notes, drawings and photographs.
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Accession numbers: 1982-074, 1984-053 The bulk of this collection was given to Stanford University, Special Collections by Mrs. Edith Haupt in July 1982. Addenda to the collection were given to the Library by Mr. Arthur Haupt in April 1984.
Biography / Administrative History
Zygmunt Haupt 1907-1975, was a native of Poland. He began his career in writing and painting after abandoning earlier studies in architecture and urban planning. Following the German invasion of Poland in 1939, Mr. Haupt escaped to Hungary, then on to France and England, where he continued to serve with Polish forces until the war ended. Mr. Haupt came to the United States after the war and became a United States citizen. He worked for 18 years for the U.S. Information Agency. During that time his writings appeared in the principal Polish ?migr? journals Wiadomosci (London) and Kultura (Paris). His book, The Paper Ring, was published for the first time in Paris in 1962 and won the Kultura literary award. In 1971 he received the annual award from the Koscielski Foundation in Geneva for his contributions to the Polish literature.
Scope and Content of Collection
The entire collection contains correspondence, literary manuscripts, a few drawings, notes, and photographs.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Chambrun, Jacques.; Chmielowiec, Michal, 1918-1974.; Czapska, Maria, 1894-1981.; Czapski, Jozef, 1896-1993.; Giedroyc, Jerzy, 1906-2000.; Grydzewski, Mieczyslaw, 1984-1970.; Hertz, Zofia, 1911-2003.; Hostowiec, Pawel.; Janta, Aleksander, 1908-1974.; Kempka, Jan.; Mayewski, Pawel, 1920-1991.; Ruszkowski, Zdzislaw, 1907-1991.; Stempowski, Jerzy, 1894-1969.; Wittlin, Jozef, 1896-1976.; Haupt, Zygmunt, 1907-1975.; Polish literature--20th century.
Container List
- Series 1: CORRESPONDENCE, 1
  - Subseries A: Professional correspondence with editors, A
    - Correspondence, 1953-1963, with Jacques Chambrun (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes English text of the "Kultura" Literary Prize that Haupt received in 1962. Also, four responses from various literary agencies regarding Haupt's inquiry of adapting Orwell's "Animal Farm" for television.
    - Correspondence, 1949-1974: with editors of "Kultura" (Paris), mainly Jerzy Giedroyc and Zofia Hertz, during 1949-1974. (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
    - Correspondence, 1948-1972: with Mieczyslaw Grydzewski and Michal Chmielowiec, editors of "Wiadomosci", a Polish literary magazine published in London. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1949-1963: with editors of "New Directions": James Laughlin, et al.. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1970: with Pawel Mayewski and Jan Kempka, the editors of "Tematy", a Polish quarterly magazine published in New York. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1947-1971: with various editors regarding eventuality of publishing Haupt's literary works. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1975: with publishers in Poland ("Czytelnik", Instytut Badan Literackich, Panstwowy Instytut Wydawniczy, and one unidentified editor). (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes correspondence with editors of literary dictionaries, business proposals of writing and translating; correspondence and information on American literary magazines, potentially interested in publishing Haupt's writings (1947-1956).
  - Subseries B: Private correspondence, B
    - Family correspondence, 1953-1975: with Haupt's sister, Zofia Daroszyna.. (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
      The letters and postcards are in Polish. Also, there are money transfer records
    - Family correspondence, 1953-1975: between Haupt and his nieces, daughters of Zofia Daroszyna, Malgorzata Holak and Teresa Darocha. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Family correspondence, 1950s-1975: with distant cousins: Janina Dziekonska (Jaska), Mieczyslaw Haupt and his daughter, Teresa, and Marian Haupt. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Friends and acquaints correspondence, 1950-197: with co-founders of "Kultura", Jozef Czapski and his sister, Maria Czapska. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Three letters, 1976: are between Edith Haupt and Maria Czapska: 1976.
    - Friends and acquaints correspondence, 1963: from Jan Fryling, a contributor to the Polish émigré press in London and Radio Free Europe. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Friends and acquaintances correspondence, 1947-1975: with Zygmunt Hladki, a Polish philosopher living in London. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Friends and acquaintances correspondence, 1950-1973: with Aleksander Janta, a Polish journalist-in-exile. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Friends and acquaintance correspondence, 1949-1974: with Andrzej Kruczkowski, a journalist and clerk of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Friends and acquaintance correspondence, 1949-1975: with Zdzislaw Ruszkowski, a Polish painter in England. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Last Ruszkowski's letter, 1988 is about donating his correspondence with Haupt to the Special Collection. Also, Ruszkowski's drawings, a catalog of paintings, and a newspaper clipping.
    - Friends and acquaintance correspondence, 1950s-1962: with Adam Sroczynski, a cadet officer in the Haupt's battery during WWII. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Friends and acquaintance correspondence, 1963-1966: with Jerzy Stempowski (pseud. Pawel Hostowiec), a Polish émigré in Berne, Switzerland. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Friends and acquaintance correspondence, 1947-1974: letter and postcards with Jozef Wittlin, a Polish novelist, essayist, and poet living in New York. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Friends and acquaintance correspondence, last names A-K, 1939-1975: (Box 2, Folder 10)
      With Eugenia Bochno, Lidia Brenner, Ann Davis, Jan Drzezdzon, S. Dziarczykowski, Jan Jarosz, Mrs. Lester F. Gilbert, Valery Goethel, Cecily Johnson, Anna Kaminska, Zofia and Stefan Korbonski, Karol & Maria Kuryluk. In Polish and English.
    - Friends and acquaintance correspondence, last names L-M, 1943-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      With J. Lebenstein, Jerzy Lerski, Wiktor Labunski, Anna Laczynska, Maria (Biba) and Boleslaw Laczynski, Astrid Meissner, Pat Murphy. Envelopes of letters of Teodor Parnicki and Stefan Paszkiewicz.
    - Friends and acquaints correspondence, last names P-Z, 1957-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      With Anna Popoff, Maria Radzyminska (an envelope and a bank transfer record), Marek Szapiro, Tymon Terlecki, Wiktor Weintraub, Margaret Wentworth-Smith, Waclaw Zagorski, Jan and Helena Zakrzewski, W. Zgorzelski.
    - Friends and acquaintances correspondence, unidentified, 1945-1974. (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Letters and postcards.
  - Subseries C: Correspondence with book dealers, C
    - Correspondence, 1953-1974: with book dealers from U.S, Great Britain, Switzerland, and France; in Polish and English. (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Also, index cards with the book titles, prices, and short reviews.
    - Correspondence, 1973-1974: with book dealers in Poland. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series 2: PERSONAL DOCUMENTS, 2
  - Miscellaneous, 1940-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Various documents such as letters, a biography note, newspaper clippings, a military-leave order from a Polish Army in France, a letter from Koscielski's Foundation informing Haupt about recognizing his writing and awarding him in 1971, library cards, etc.
  - Photographs: mainly black and white photos of Haupt, his family, and friends. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Obituary: sympathy letters, newspaper clippings, and telegrams. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series 3: ART WORKS, 3
  - Drawings of people, horses, and buildings. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs: black and white photographs of Haupt's paintings. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1941-1949: with Haupt's works. (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1948-1949: art exhibitions and Haupt's paintings. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence regarding various exhibitions of Haupt's paintings. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series 4: LITERARY WORKS, 4
  - Subseries A: Various formats or miscellaneous, A
    - Haupt's poems in English (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Includes the "Greenie Nothing" (sent to Furioso poetry contest) and "The Hawk". Polish translations of the poems by Edgar Lee Masters. Also, one unidentified piece in Polish.
    - Criticism (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Multiple copies of a few articles and notes on the U.S. literary magazines, literature, and some biographical pieces about American writers and poets (E.E. Cummings, Henry James, and others).
    - Multiple copies of an article on life and works of Henry James. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Short article and its rough draft written in 1955 in commemoration of the centenary of death of Adam Mickiewicz, a Polish poet; a short piece about thousand-year anniversary of Poland in aspect of the communist regime (in English). (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Interviews and discussion, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Two slightly various records of discussion among Polish intellectuals called "An Adventure in Cybernetics", which took place at the office of "Nowa Kultura", a Warsaw literary weekly.
    - Interviews and discussion (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Multiple copies of interviews about European and American novel development (in Polish and English) and an interview on American poetry with Randall Jarrell
    - Multiple copies of "Kartoteka" in Polish [written on 3.21.62] and its English version "Dossier;" other materials (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Also "Paderewski" (Polish), "Jan Kardynal Krol, Arcybiskup Filadelfii" (in Polish and English), "Stalin o jezykoznawstwie" (in Polish), Vademecum pisarza i anonsera radiowego (Polish), "Reputation of Warsaw Black Book" (in English), "Reputation of American Blac Book" (in English), multiple copies of "The Kosciuszko Foundation" (in Polish and English).
    - Multiple copies of "Gaude mater Polonia (Box 3, Folder 17)
      A report on the First Congress of Scholars and Scientists sponsored by The Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America, in observance of Polish Millenium, held at Columbia University in New York (English and Polish).
    - "The symbol and the stone" (in Polish and English), "The Art imitates life: on the American Alfred Jurzykowski Foundation" (in English), radio broadcast, such as "A feast of 16th Squadron" (in Polish). (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Subseries B: Short stories in Polish, B
    - Two copies of "Cyrk" (Circus), two copies of "Wiezien z Isle of Ely" (The Prisoner of Isle of Ely) (the second copy incomplete), two copies of "Z Roxolanii" (From Roxolania). (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Numerous copies (some of them complete) of "Dzisiaj, przedwczoraj, wczoraj, jutro" (Today, The Day Before, Yesterday, Tomorrow). (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Szpica and two copies of "Ulan Czuchnowski". (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Multiple copies of "Do dwu razy sztuka" (some of them complete, some unreadable). (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Multiple copies (not complete) of two stories "Nietota" and "Der Hampelmann" (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Some pages have handwritten editorial revisions (most likely made by Haupt).
    - Multiple typescripts (not complete) copies of stories called "Perekotypole", "Balon", "Gwiazda Syberii" (some with handwritten revisions). (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Multiple copies, perhaps stories called "Swiaty", "Wyspy Galapagos", and "Wyprawa na Mount Everest", and some others. (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Multiple copies of typescripts and manuscripts of stories "Wyjatek z powiesci" and "Polonez na pozegnanie ojczyzny". (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Multiple copies of manuscripts and typescripts of "Ludzie na wsi", "Rigor mortis", "Pejzaz Armorykanski", "Golebie z Placu Teodora", "Ulan Czuchnowski". (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Typescripts of "Entropia" in Polish (some pages in English), and fragments of other stories. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Multiple copies of "Powrot", "O Pannie herbu Panna na Niedzwiedziu", "Cztery pory roku", and other stories. (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Mostly typescripts, some with revisions.
    - Multiple copies of "Henry Bush i jego samolot", "Luizjana", "Wiezien z Isle of Ely", "Dziwnie bylo bardzo, bo...", "Poker w Gorganach", "W szkole realnej" (first version), "Do dwu razy sztuka", "W internacie ks.ks. Zmartwychwstancow", "Pejzaz ze wschodu slonca", "Dzien targowy", "To ja sam jestem Emma Bovary". (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
    - Multiple typescripts (mostly) and manuscripts of "Golebie z Placu Teodora", "Odwilz", "Kulig", "Wyjazd o swicie", "Appendicitis", "Wyspy Galapagos i wyprawa na Mount Everest", "Polonez na pozegnanie ojczyzny", "Pejzaz", "Matuzalem", "Czuchnowski", "Ogrod jezuicki", "Szklo na ulicy", "P.I.M.", "Sur le Pont d'Avignion", "W drodze na morzu", "Cyrk" (some of them are drafts, some have hand written revisions). (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
      (some of them are drafts, some have hand written revisions).
    - Typescripts of "Dziwnie bylo bardzo, bo..." (not complete), "Jezdziec bez glowy", "Marsylianka", "Dziewczynka z nozkami na ksiezycach" (a few pages only). (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Typescripts of "Barbarzyncy", "Kawaler z morskiej pianki", "Henry Bush" (last one not complete). (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Typescripts of "Z kroniki o latajacym domu" (not complete, multiple copies), "Szpica" (fragments), "Strachy ". (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Typescripts of "Czuwanie i stypa" (not complete), "W Paryzu i Arkadii", "Coup de grace", "O Stefci, o Chaimie Immerglücku i o scytyjskich bransoletkach" (multiple copies, some with handwritten revisions, not complete), "Poker w Gorganach" (a few pages), and multiple copies of "Meine liebe Mutter, sei stolz, Ich trage die Fahne". (Box 6, Folder 7-x)
    - Typescripts of "Czuwanie i stypa" (not complete), "W Paryzu i Arkadii", "Coup de grace", "O Stefci, o Chaimie Immerglücku i o scytyjskich bransoletkach" (multiple copies, some with handwritten revisions, not complete), "Poker w Gorganach" (a few pages), and multiple copies of "Meine liebe Mutter, sei stolz, Ich trage die Fahne". (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Typescripts of "Co nowego w kinie?", "Coup de grace" (with revisions), W Paryzu i w Arkadii" (with Polish diacritics inserted manualy), "O Stefci..." (multiple copies), and "Poker w Gorganach". (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Typescripts of "Meine liebe Mutter, sei Stolz, Ich trage die Fahne", "Madrygal dla Anusi", "Polowanie wigilijne z Maupassantem", "Bialy Mazur", "P.I.M.", "Jak wiosna przyjechala", and "Golebie z Placu Teodora". (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Accurate copies of the stories sent to "Kultura" on 10/06/1971 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      "Lutnia", "Lili Marlene", "To ja sam jestem Emma Bovary", "Nietota", "Perekotypole".
    - Accurate copies of the stories sent to "Kultura" on 10/06/1971 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      "El Pelele", "Baskijski diabel", "Balon", "Trzy", "Do dwu razy sztuka", "Meldunek o nieprzybyciu Welnowskiego", and "Swiaty".
    - Accurate copies of the last stories sent to "Kultura" on 4/10/1972 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      "Ostatni zbior opowiadan" ("The Last Collection of Short Stories": "Wstep" (Introduction), "Lutnia", "Lili Marlene", "To ja sam jestem Emma Bovary", "Dwie wizyty", "Nietota", and "Perekotypole".
    - Accurate copies of the last stories sent to "Kultura" on 4/10/1972 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      "Ostatni zbior opowiadan" ("The Last Collection of Short Stories": "El Pelele", "Baskijski diabel", "Balon", "Trzy", "Swiaty", and "Warianty".
    - Accurate copies of the last stories sent to "Kultura" on 4/10/1972 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      "Ostatni zbior opowiadan (The Last Collection of Short Stories"): "Strachy", "Zabawa w 'zielone'", "Szpica", "Do dwu razy sztuka", "Meldunek o nieprzybyciu Welnowskiego", Wiezien z Isle of Ely", and "Z Laczczyny".
    - Six stories from "The Paper Ring" (Box 8, Folder 2)
      "The Wake and the Repast", "What's New at the Movies?", "Coup de Grace", "In Paris and in Arcadia", "The Scytian Bracelet", and "Playing Poker".
    - Meine liebe Mutter, sei Stolz, Ich trage die Fahne, "Madrigal", The Rain", "The Shooting Party with Maupassant", "Tierra del Fuego", "Meteorology", "The Spring", "The Doves of Theodora Square", "Odd Items, Because...", and "The Headless Rider". (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - La Marseillaise "The Girl with Her Heels Set on Half Moons". "Barbarians Are Looking at the Landscape of the Conquered Country", "The Meerschaum Man", "Sunrise With Steel Objects", "Henry Bush and His Stinson", " Chronicle Concerning a Flying House", and "The Paper Ring". (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - The Paper Ring, a collection of short stories in English (translated from Polish by the author, edited by his son, Arthur, in 1981) on acid free paper. (Box 8, Folder 5-7)
  - Subseries C: Fragments and drafts, C
    - Various short stories and other prose in Polish, most of them unidentified (Box 9, Folder 1-x)
      Includes "Pamietnik znaleziony w Sabre-Tache porucznika Pulku Strzelcow Konnych Gwardii Krolestwa Polskiego".
    - Various short stories and other prose in Polish, most of them unidentified (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
    - Manuscript of an unidentified fragment of a story in Polish. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Z cyklu Kultury, Najnowsza geografia Polski albo przewodnik po Zolkwi, i jej pamiatkach, multicopies of prose about Zolkiew, a Ukrainian town, and "Lutnia". (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
    - A collection of vocabulary - a dictionary project that includes student-, soldier-, jazz-, and hippie- related terms. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Subseries D: Notes, D
    - Folders include notes on various readings, some excerpts, and translations (English, Polish, French, German, Latin, and Ukrainian). (Box 10, Folder 8-10)
      The folder contains a few drawings, the notes on a Roman army, Polish cavalry and horse types, and literary translations. There are typed and hand-written notes. Some of them are unreadable.
  - Subseries E: Translations, mostly from English to Polish, E
    - Haupt's translation of a story by the Polish writer Marek Hlasko called "W dzien smierci Jego" (On the Day of His Death). (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Haupt's Polish translation of "The Turn of the Screw" by Henry James (chapters I, IV, and XII only) (handwritten revisions), and six pages of notes and drawings by Haupt. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Haupt's notes on Robert Frost, as well as translations of his writings (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Includes "Powrot najemnika", multiple copies of "Czarownica z Coos", "Zamysl", "Skarby skarb", "Przystanawszy pod lasem w zimowy wieczor", Arthur Koestler's "Inteligencja" (typescript and manuscript), Robert Lowell's "The Quaker Graveyard in Nantucket", the original in English and multiple copies of translations, some with handwritten revisions, and W.H. Auden's "Ach co to za glos?"
    - Haupt's note on James Agee's in English and Polish as well as translations of some of his work. (Box 11, Folder 4)
      Includes "Pochwalmy teraz slawnych ludzi" (multiple copies, some with handwritten revisions), multiple copies of a few pages with translation of Henry James' "The Pupil", E.E. Cummings' "The Enormous Room".
  - Subseries F: The "Voice of America" and the United States Information Agency (USIA) broadcast scripts (1951-1960), F
    - An envelope addressed to Zygmunt Haupt from USIA, and a script of a broadcast "American Poles Protest Against Persecution of Church in Poland" [n.d.]; other works listed below. (Box 11, Folder 5)
      "On the Congress of Polish Science in Warsaw" (8.1.51-8.15.51),[6.30.51], "Warsaw Uprising Anniversary [8.1.51] - damaged by water, "Anniversary of the Battle of Warsaw 1920" [8.15.51], "Soviet Invasion of Poland in 1939"[9.17.51], American Airmen Over Warsaw 7 Years Ago [9.18.51], "Fall of Warsaw in 1939" [9.27.51]. All of the pieces are in English.
    - October - November of 1951 scripts: "Polish Youth and Warsaw Uprising" [10.1.51] - the only piece in English, "Nauka w Polsce i swiecie wspolczesnym" [10.7.51; 10.14.51; 10.28.51], "Pulaski Day Parade" [10.11.51] (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - December 1951- January of 1952 scripts in Polish (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Among them "The Study of Contemporary Poland and Contemporary World" [12.9.51], "Full Cast of Youth Show in Christmas Party" [12.23.51], "Birthday of Adam Mickiewicz" [12.23.51], "Christmas Eve Super" [12.24.51], "A Christmas Carol" [12.25.51], "Polish Christmas" [12.25.51], "A Year in the Making" [12.30.51], ], "The Study of Contemporary Poland and Contemporary World" [1.13.52; 1.20.52;1.27.52], and "The Foundation of University of Lwow" [1.20.52], and "Polish Uprising 1863" [1.23.52].
    - February - April of 1952 scripts in Polish (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Includes "Birthday of Stefan Zeromski" [2.14.52], "The Study of Contemporary Poland and Contemporary World" [2.17.52; 2.24.52; 4.14.52], "Szymanowski Death Anniversary" [3.31.52], and "Polish-Soviet Borderline" [4.9.52].
    - May - July of 1952 scripts in Polish (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Includes "Great Polish Constitution of May Third, 1791" [5.3.52], "Battle of Monte Cassino Anniversary" [5.18.52], "From Soviet Labor Camps to Monte Cassino" [5.18.52], "Stalin's Unwanted Gift to Poland" [5.25.52], "Stalin promises a Free Poland" [5.27.52], "In Memory of Polish Historian Lelewel" [5.3.52], "Death of John Dewey" [6.2.52], "Maria Curie-Sklodowska" [7.3.52; 7.6.52], "Independence Day" [7.4.52], "On the Eve of Polish Youth Rally" [7.18.52], "Communist's Independence Day in Poland" [7.22.52], and "Birthday of Jan Matejko, Polish Painter" [7.25.52].
    - August - October of 1952 scripts in Polish (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Includes "Warsaw Uprising 1944: The Beginning" [8.1.52], "USSR Invades Poland September 17, 1939" [9.17.52], "Fourth Partition of Poland" [9.28.52], "Analysis of Warsaw Uprising" [10.1.52], "Aftermath of Warsaw Uprising" [10.3.52], "Soviets Change Names of Polish Cities" [10.10.52], "Death of Frederic Chopin" [10.17.52], and "Stalin Corrupts Polish Literary Life" [31.10.52].
    - November - December of 1952 scripts in Polish (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Includes "Polish Independence Day" [11.11.52], "Polish-Soviet Friendship" [11.14.52], "Anniversary of Death of Adam Mickiewicz" [11.26.52], "Polish Uprising of November 1830" [11.28.52] - three various copies, "Death Anniversary of Stanislaw Reymont, Birth Anniversary of Jan Kasprowicz" [12.12.52], "Silone and His Polish Counterpart Stryjkowski" [12.19.52], "Birth Anniversary of Adam Mickiewicz, Death Anniversary of Juliusz Slowacki" [12.12.52], "Western Writers on Soviet Russia" [12.26.52].
    - Various scripts in Polish, with no specific dates assigned, but numbers and the year 1952 only (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Includes "From the Communist Jungle" (210), "Ideology of Communism" (262), "Stalinism Abuses Truth" (289), "Polish Philosophy in Quandary" (412), "Wojtek Dolinski: Child-Actor of Broadway" (424), "We Read What We Please" (466), "Americana/ Polio Inoculation" (550), "Gallery of Great Polish Statesmen: General Wladyslaw Sikorski", "Gallery of Great Polish Statesmen: Stanislaw Thugutt", "Pilot Jazwinski: Bringing Message From Polish Youth"-two copies, "William Oatis Story".
    - An introduction to and copies of a broadcast script of "Animal Farm", by George Orwell. (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
      All pieces, I-XX, are in Polish.
    - Introduction to and copies of a broadcast script of "Darkness in Noon" by Arthur Koestler (Ciemnosc w poludnie, albo Co sie stalo z towarzyszem Wieslawem?) (most likely, it was written in 1952). (Box 12, Folder 7-8)